<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Fugitive statesman, in requital for The perplex'd prince</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R112</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13165764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13165764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 417:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Fugitive statesman, in requital for The perplex'd prince</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Grover,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An attack on Lord Shaftesbury.</note>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Page 2 is tightly bound with loss of print; pages 54 and 63 are faded in the filmed copy. Beginning-page 15 photographed from Bodleian Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683.</term>
               <term>Perplex'd prince.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:1"/>
            <p>THE FUGITIVE STATESMAN, IN REQUITAL FOR THE Perplex'd Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Grover,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Faction, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the many Inſtances they have ſo frequently given of their Spleen and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tned to the Government, hardly ever ſhewed their Malice more in any one particular, than in the Buſineſs of the <hi>Black Box,</hi> which furniſh'd a
<pb facs="tcp:98237:3"/> Pretext to a Libel, call'd <hi>The Perplex'd Prince;</hi> which, tho' but poorly writ, yet the maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Deſign being to poyſon Peoples Minds with an Opinion of ſome Probability and Truth in that Matter. It was thought fit in Return, to ſhew the World one of their Principal Heroes, in his true Colours. How well ſoever his Picture may have been drawn by others, yet ſome Features,
<pb facs="tcp:98237:3"/> Lines perhaps may have eſcaped their Pencills, which are coucht here in the Landskip of that <hi>Arch Ttaytor's</hi> Life. A Mirrour of him can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too often looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; that one may avoid falling into the Snare of thoſe wicked, wretched <hi>Partizans</hi> he has left behind him, who never ceaſe undermining the Foundations of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually brewing Sedition,
<pb facs="tcp:98237:4"/> with the higheſt Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, after all the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and repeated Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons of their Gracious Prince and Sovereign: Tho' they can have now no Hopes, no Proſpect of ever bringing about their tug'd for <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy;</hi> yet we ſtill daily ſee freſh Inſtances of their reſtleſs Endeavors to that End, ſo that one would think they do not yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of effecting their Purpoſes, notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:98237:4"/> they have loſt their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron.</hi> But it is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their good Intentions will be Crown'd with the ſame Fate with that of the wicked <hi>Achitophel;</hi> and that they now too will be thinking of ſetting their Houſes in Order. It's high time; for they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo much the Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Mankind, that they can expect but little Comfort in this World; and I am afraid, unleſs they give other Teſtimonies
<pb facs="tcp:98237:5"/> than they have yet done of their good Nature and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, they are not to expect much Happineſs and Felicity in that to come. How pernicious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have proved both to Church and State, they would be glad to ſee they had a due Sence of their former practiſes; and could they be but prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with to ask Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they would undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly obtain their Pardon: But it is ſo much their
<pb facs="tcp:98237:5"/> Nature, and they ſeem ſo obſtinately bent upon doing Miſchief, that there is no probability of their ever being perſwaded to forſake their evil ways. And ſince no Counſels do avail for the reducing them to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: nor to court them from deſtruction, we muſt e'en abandon them to their Fate, which undoubtedly at length will do them Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and reward them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Merits.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98237:6"/>
            <head>THE Fugitive Stateſman.</head>
            <div n="1-42" type="pages">
               <p>THE Land of <hi>Judah</hi> had never attained to that refinedneſs in Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as under the Reign of <hi>David;</hi> that Prince having overcome all his Enemies both Forreign and Domeſtick, and eſtabliſhed himſelf by his juſt and gentle Government, as well in the Hearts of his People, as upon the Throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> gave up thoſe hours which are ſo neceſſary for Refreſhment to amorous Deſigns, and was herein ſo univerſally imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by all his Subjects, that there was none of what Age and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98237:7"/> Condition ſoever but had ſome Intrigue; inſomuch that by this general Practice, there was no manner of Artifice, Contrivance, or Stratagem for the well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging an Amour, but what was brought to the higheſt Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, during the time of his ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scepter.</p>
               <p>During the Wars that were between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iſhboſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> for the Crown of <hi>Iſrael, Abner</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only the Juſtice of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Cauſe, but that it would be likewiſe impoſſible for the Hſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per's Son, to withſtand the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and good Fortune of the King of <hi>Judah;</hi> did privily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand make Offers of Submiſſion unto his Rightful Prince, with the Forces under his Command which <hi>David</hi> accepted of, upon Condition of bringing him again <hi>Michal</hi> his Wife, whom <hi>Saul</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father had given to <hi>Phalti:</hi> Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98237:7"/> Treaty was managed by <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> and that with ſo much Art and Cunning as procured all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Succeſs to <hi>David,</hi> and proved finally deſtructive to his Enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jezabel, Michal</hi>'s youngeſt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter having ſtaid with her during the late Troubles, was now wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to accompany her to Court; and in the ſeveral Converſations that <hi>Achitophel</hi> had with <hi>Jezabel</hi> upon that Occaſion, he was ſo cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated with the Wit and Beauty of that Princeſs, as made him think the higheſt Felicity conſiſted in the poſſeſſion of a Heart adorned with ſo many Charms; and as her Excellencies inſpired him with Amorous Thoughts, ſo they infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him with the Ambition to attempt the inſinuating himſelf into her Favour and Affections.</p>
               <p>This he did not diſpair of effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, he knew his own Talents,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98237:8"/> he knew none more fit than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for cloſe Deſigns and crooked Counſels; he was a Man ſagacious and bold, had not only all the Arts of a Miniſter of State, but was as dexterous in the well managing an Amorous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue; he knew that <hi>Jezabel</hi> was Ambitious, and had had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſome Kindneſs for <hi>David,</hi> which was now turned into a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Reſentment, upon his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preferred <hi>Bathſheba</hi> before her. All theſe Circumſtances concurring to the flattering his Hopes, he reſolved to embark in this Deſign, notwithſtanding he had not all the Advantages of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as concur to the making a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and an agreeable Gallant.</p>
               <p>He was not long without find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Occaſion to make known to her his Paſſion, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in ſuch Terms as were moſt capable of Perſuaſion, and fitteſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98237:8"/> for Inſinuation: But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Figure he made in the State, and the conſiderable Intereſt he had both in Court and elſewhere, he met with more Severity than he expected, and was treated with ſome ſort of Scorn and Diſdain, ſhe having that Opinion of her Charms, as to think all Homages unworthy of her Allowance, that were not made by Crowned Heads.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Flames were too raging to be ſtifled by this Reſiſtance, and as it was one branch of his Character to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake difficult Attempts, and to perſevere until he had brought to paſs his Deſigns, this Oppoſition did but the more whet his Deſires, and make him ſet the greater Value upon the Object he adored. Thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved never to deſiſt until he had accompliſhed his Aim, and for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98237:9"/> that purpoſe he beſieged her with continual Aſſiduities, informed her conſtantly of all the Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the Cabinet Councils at Court, and ſecret Cabals in the City, and by theſe means ſooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her intrigueing and aſſpiring Temper, and ſo by degrees inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating himſelf into her Breaſt, he became in a ſhort time a very extraordinary Favourite.</p>
               <p>He had now changed his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in the management of this Intrigue, He forbore ſpeaking to her of Love, expreſſing no Paſſion but for her Service, and her intereſt, telling her that no Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs upon the Earth, would ſo well become a Throne as ſhe, that undoubtedly Providence would one day do her and it ſelf the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as to give her the Crown of all <hi>Aſia.</hi> And when that any great Sovereign's Bed was vacant, he ſeem'd grieved that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98237:9"/> would not allow of a Match, that ſo he might have ſhown his Zeal for her Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in uſing his Intereſt for the bringing it to paſs. By ſuch like Diſcourſes as theſe, did he win upon her haughty Humour, and became to that degree her Boſom Friend, that imagining ſhe could not expect ever to find a Perſon ſo proper as <hi>Achitophel</hi> to make her Confident, nor one more capable of putting in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution her fatal Deſigns, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to eaſe her Heart of thoſe tormenting Thoughts, which ſhe there kept pent up, by making <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Breaſt the Repoſitory of them. Thus one day after having acquainted her with the Paſſages at Court, and entertained her for a long while with the Zeal he had for her Service: My Lord, ſaid ſhe, to <hi>Achitophel,</hi> I am ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of your good Intentions, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98237:10"/> am glad to find your Love chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a Paſſion for my Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and to ſhew you how far you have won upon me, by the repeated Inſtances of your good Will and Favour, I am willing to unboſom to you my moſt ſecret Thoughts, and let you know what reaſon I have to be a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content. You may remember, continued ſhe, how that upon my Siſter <hi>Michal</hi>'s Marriage to <hi>David,</hi> I fell ill of a Feaver, and I muſt own, though not without a Bluſh, that his good Meen, his Wit, in ſhort, all thoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he had received both from Art and Nature, had made ſome Impreſſion upon my Heart, and if I was not flattered I might have expected to have made the like in his; but notwithſtanding all my endearing Carriage, I found him inſenſible to all my Favours, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Michal</hi> could he adore.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98237:10"/> She was the Object of all his Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and I of his Scorn and Neglect. Nevertheleſs, I patiently bore with this Preference, ſince it was ſupported and confirmed by the Will of <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſince he was wholly ignorant of the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I entertained, tho I had made all the Advances poſſible to hint to him how favourably his Vows would be heard if paid to me, and told him all ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing things, as were conſiſtent with the Glory of a Princeſs of my Rank: But <hi>David</hi> was ſo blinded with his Paſſion for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal,</hi> that he had no Eyes for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Charms. However in a ſhort time you know the Change at Court, <hi>David</hi> was drove from thence. I know it Madam, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Achitophel,</hi> for I am ſure, I was the chief occaſion of his Exile and Sufferings, but pardon the Interruption, Madam, you ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98237:11"/> hear more of that hereafter. You know <hi>David</hi> was baniſhed the Court, renewed ſhe, you know <hi>Michal</hi> his Wife was given by <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Phal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i,</hi> the Son of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> and now my Love made me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain freſh Hopes, I fancied <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> would never condeſcend to a Reconciliation with a Perſon, who had yielded to give her ſelf to another, I had reaſon to expect <hi>David</hi> would certainly one day mount the Throne being ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally rooted in the Affections of the People, and I had the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to believe that all the twelve Tribes could not furniſh a Perſon fitter to ſhare with him in his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries than my ſelf. And when accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he returned, and you were ſent to bring <hi>Michal</hi> back, my hopes revived more ſtrong than ever; for though I might have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended he might have had ſome inclination ſtill left for her,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98237:11"/> yet knowing how much ſhe had loſt of her former Charms ſince their laſt Interview I did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair of undermining her, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in her place. This made me the more eager to accompany her to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where I was crue by diſappointed of all my Expectations. <hi>Michal</hi> 'tis true has not that ſhare in <hi>David</hi>'s Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduities ſhe formerly poſſeſſed, 'tis <hi>Bathſheba</hi> now that is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of his Affections, ſhe reigns ſovereignly in his Breaſt, I and my Family are dayly more negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and depreſſed, and all for a Perſon much beneath my Rank, and, may be, Merits. Here ſhe pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and the wily <hi>Achitophel,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſuming the Diſcourſe, told her that he had been long ſenſible of the Indignities ſhe ſuffered, and as long deſirous of procuring the means of doing her Juſtice, and of furniſhing her with Occaſions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98237:12"/> to ſhew her Reſentment. It is not only the Outrages, perſued he, that are done to all thoſe Charms you poſſes in ſo ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign a Degree, and the Paſſion I have in all that concerns you, that prompts me to Revenge, I have ſome Reaſons of my own, that might pretend to ſpur me to it, if yours, Madam, alone were not ſufficient to put me upon the Wing. I am neglected too at Court, <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s Conuſels are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before mine, and I am not thought worthy of having that ſhare in the preſent management of Affairs, that perhaps I am ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. I am ſuſpected of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill inclined to the Family and Practices of your Father <hi>Saul;</hi> and they have not yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the part I had in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſmal Revolutions. And I muſt indeed confeſs, I was never over-well affected to Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98237:12"/> in Common-wealths, the braveſt and wiſeſt have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly their ſhare: But in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy all goes generally by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Affection, and a Man cannot be thought a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject without being a Slave, and that Servility is in my Mind incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with a generous Temper. Thus my natural Diſpoſition led me to promote and foment the late Troubles, and I found <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> then, though ſo young, yet ſo extraordinarily gifted, that I foreſaw he would have but little need of the Miniſtry of others, and I diſpaired of ever having any thing to do in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs his Excluſion was obtained. This ſet me to work, and I found more eaſe than I expected in my undertaking; People were eaſily decoyed with Alarums of Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Properties, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98237:13"/> of their Liberties; we ſcattered Rumours abroad of the extraordinary Influence the <hi>Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi> had at Court, and of the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood there was of their introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Religion, if not ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly prevented and vigorouſly oppoſed. Theſe Bates not only took with the ſilly People but with the whole <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> they entered into Covenants, and by United Forces, they at length found the means to deprive the King both of his Crown and Life, and expel the Heir the Kingdom. Yet all we who had firſt proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted this Revolution, were fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in our Hopes, for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my we made uſe of uſurped the Power we had promiſed our ſelves, but then it was too late, we were conſtrained to ſubmit to the Arbitrary Temper of the Sword, and ſo brought upon the People what they had ſo much
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98237:13"/> dreaded, and what many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them had endeavoured to prevent to the loſs of their Fortunes, and their Lives, and thus did we occaſion all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that a whole Nation in Combuſtion can ſuffer, without any Benefit to our ſelves, but we were forced to diſſemble, and content our ſelves to ſtand as Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to the Uſurper. But he being dead, and ſilly <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> upon the Throne, we fell again to contriving how to out him thence, and to place our ſelves in his ſtead. By theſe means our Party being divided, the People too generally affected to their promiſed Prince <hi>David,</hi> and one of our Chief Leaders upon our Backs with an Army, with which he favoured the Kings Return: All theſe things, I ſay, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to make me diſpair of my own Advancement, and to ſee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98237:14"/> His Reſtitution unavoidable, I thought it was beſt to ſhift for my ſelf betimes, and therefore ſeemed as Zealous for His Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Crown, as any of his trueſt and antienteſt Friends; this made ſome way for the bringing me into Favour, I was crowned with new Honours for my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in that great Revolution, had a conſiderable ſhare in the management of publick Affairs, had conferred upon me Offices of Truſt, ſuch as were both benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and honourable too in the Minds of the Vulgar, but yet I was not ſatisfied, I could not but ſtill think it ſervile and ſlaviſh to truckle under an other, and did not yet diſpair of one day attaining to be the Head of all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> knowing the Nature of the <hi>Jews</hi> to be ſuch, as that they ſhewed their Humour more than their Humour more than their Loyalty in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98237:14"/> back <hi>David</hi> and ſetting him on the Throne. I knew a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth was their Golden Calf, and I muſt confeſs, I did not expect they would have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed ſo long. I uſed all the Arts imaginable to raiſe Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies between the Prince and his People; I promoted their giving of Monies, and the raiſing of Taxes, and then ſcattered Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours abroad of the ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſquandring away the Revenues; finding this to take my Hopes revived, I proceeded on to the giving the Prince ſuch Counſels, as I knew muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity leſſen him in his Peoples Affections: That is, I adviſed the King to joyn with <hi>Pharoah,</hi> againſt <hi>Tyre,</hi> I adviſed the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Triple Bond, on which the ſafety of all <hi>Aſia</hi> did depend, I adviſed the ſhutting up the Treaſury, by which thouſands
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98237:15"/> came to ſuffer want, I adviſed a Toleration of all Religions, which underhand, I gave out was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Court, to make way for the Religion of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites,</hi> ſo hated by the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Nation. By theſe and other Counſels as Deſtructive, I found I had pretty well further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Deſign: Now, none like me could have effected all theſe things. I had firſt ſupplanted the Juſt, the Wiſe and Learned <hi>Abethdin,</hi> and then <hi>David</hi> having truſted me with the Principal management of Affairs, I effected all theſe things, rather by ſurprize than by the King's Allowance and Conſent. But now Prudent <hi>David</hi> began to ſuſpect my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and having found my Counſels and Meaſures deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Government, and the Nations Intereſts, he diſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me the Court, and ſent me
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98237:15"/> among my Friends in the City: There I fomented the Flames I had already kindled, I gave out that <hi>Solomon</hi> the next Heir was a <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> that the Influence he had over the King might be fatal to the Religion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that if he had not already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the King, it was to be feared he would in time, or at leaſt, he would not fail when he came to the Crown himſelf to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Idolatry of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites,</hi> to the downfal of the true Church, and to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Peoples Liberties and Properties; the pamper'd <hi>Jews</hi> always inclined to rebel found this Cry too ſuitable to their Natures not to go along with it, they fell a murmuring, bawling out againſt Arbitrary Counſels, and a Change of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> it ſelf was at length ſo infected, by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98237:16"/> Care I had taken, that ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhould be elected as were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to Sedition, and Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Monarchy: The <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> I ſay, it ſelf, grew at length ſo infected, as to deny the King the neceſſary Aids for the ſupporting the Government, and defend his Subjects, and his Allies, againſt the growing and formidable Power of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> for I had poyſoned them with an Opinion, that what they ſhould give, how neceſſary ſoever, would be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to their Oppreſſion, and not in their Defence, againſt the Enemies of the Kingdom. Thus, whenever Armies were raiſed by their Conſent for the common Safety, I ſpread abroad Rumors that the Court intended to make uſe of them, for the putting in Execution Arbitrary Deſigns; Thus were they ſtill caſhier'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Buſineſs was effected for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98237:16"/> which they were raiſed. This both redoubled the Peoples Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage, and encreaſed their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs againſt the management at the Helm, being perſwaded the Government had decoyed them into the raiſing of Forces to cut their own Throats. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Poyſon I had ſcattered, <hi>David</hi> had ſtill that Influence over the Hearts of his People, that nothing could faſten the leaſt Suſpicion upon him. <hi>Solomon</hi> his Heir indeed received ſeveral Outrages in many En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters. We had work'd the Mobile up to a Belief, that he was a Favourer of Arbitrary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that he went full of the Revenge for <hi>David</hi>'s and his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering which he would not fail of cruelly executing, whenſoever he had an opportunity for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that he was labouring to reſtore the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> and their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98237:17"/> Faction, and out thoſe who were both numerous and conſiderable, who were in Poſſeſſion of their Eſtates. Theſe were terrible Alarums, they knew that this Prince had to Perfection, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Valour, they knew he never undertook any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effecting it; ſo as that they could not think themſelves too cautious in ſecuring themſelves againſt all Events. Thus did the whole Land ring with great Complaints of this great and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Prince. And pray you, Madam, obſerve here the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the People, and for how little a while the greateſt Virtues are in their eſteem; this glorious Prince, had in a thouſand Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, hazarded his Life, and all in their Defence, againſt their Enemies, and had got ſuch Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories as will make him admired by all Ages. But his Virtues in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98237:17"/> Peace, were no leſs admirable than his Qualifications in War. He was renowned for his Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice; his Gratitude was ſo great that he was never at reſt until he had tenfold reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Service that had been done him. Theſe are only Patterns of his unbounded Merits; yet the ſilly Multitude were eaſily wheedled in to a belief that this Prince was a Promoter of their ruine: though he had ſo often and ſo prodigally ventured his Blood and all in their Defence. Yet you ſee, Madam, how eaſily they were exaſperated againſt a Perſon they owed ſo much to, and how a few Arts and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rumours wrought them up to a Ferment, and the higheſt pitch of Ingratitude. But what thoſe Arts were, Madam, I muſt take another occaſion to acquaint you, having at preſent to meet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98237:18"/> 
                  <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and ſome others at a Rendezvous upon Matters of great Moment, which you ſhall not fail of knowing as ſoon as ever things are brought to any Ripeneſs, and I believe that you will not fail too of owning that never any Zeal and Paſſion could parallel that which I have for your Concerns. Thereupon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his leave he went to the Rendezvous, where he found <hi>Abſolom, Zimri, Nadab, Shimei, Corah, Iſhban, Belial, Rabſheka, Judas, Phaleg, Ben-Jochanan, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack, Og</hi> and <hi>Doeg,</hi> with many others of all ſorts and Conditions. Some of theſe were to head, countenance and give renown to the Party, others were to ſow and ſcatter Sedition: Each had a peculiar Talent for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that was allotted him, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> was a Prince endued with all the Qualities proper to win
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98237:18"/> the Hearts of the People, he was beautiful above all the Men of his Time, had by early Conqueſts in the Wars of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Neighbors gain'd mighty Renown and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, was <hi>David</hi>'s Son, which was ſufficient to entitle him to be the Darling of all the Tribes: Thus the Gracefulneſs of his Meen, the Benignity of his Temper, the Comlineſs of his Perſon, and the Vaſtneſs of his Performances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charms capable of inſinuating themſelves into the Affections of Perſons of all Conditions: None ſo generally adored, none ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally celebrated as was <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> By this Prince it was that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> thought moſt fit to lure and decoy to his Party, if not the generality of all the Tribes, at leaſt, the diſſenting Sects of the <hi>Jews:</hi> Not that this wily Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician deſign'd or intended his Greatneſs, but for that he knew
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98237:19"/> that having no juſt Title to the Crown, he muſt always neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily depend upon him and his Faction, until that having thus divided and deſtroyed the Royal Family, by its Domeſtical Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he might by that means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Monarchy into a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or Democracy. Thus he had been long beſieging him with all the Arts of a crafty Stateſman, had flattered him with the Dominion he had over the Peoples Affections, but then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto him how highly derogating it was to his Honour, for him to ſpend his days in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Eaſe, after he had begun ſo glorious a Career, that all his Lawrels would tarniſh and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade away, unleſs cultivated by new Efforts and Undertakings, that his Father <hi>David</hi> was now in the Declenſion of his Age, and now leſſened too in the Minds of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98237:19"/> People, as being ſuſpected of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving favoured the late Plot of the <hi>Jebuſites, Solomon,</hi> though a Prince endued with all the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues worthy of, and fit to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a Throne, yet being thought a <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> the People did but the more abhor him for his good Qualifications, and thought that they only tended to the rendring him the more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of introducing that change, which they fancied he deſigned, and conſequently their own Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: That he had found the way to eſtrange People's Hearts from <hi>David,</hi> and that the general Cry was for Religion, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and Liberty, with ſeveral other Arguments; as that being ſet up by the People, they would be the more fond of him as a Creature of their own making, and though his Command were limitted, yet in caſe of ill Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98237:20"/> upon any occaſion, he might impute it to that Limitation, and to the ſhortneſs of his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then ended his Haran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with new Eulogies upon his former Conduct and Actions.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s generous Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per being ſooth'd by Praiſe and Flattery, and blinded by Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the only Vice of great Souls, was almoſt ready to yield to the Artifices of this Fox, when for a while the Royal Blood ſtrugling ſtill in him, he replyed, that he had no pretext to take up Arms for the publick Liberty, that his Father govern'd with unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd right, that he was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Mankind, and the Faith's Defender, that he was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by all to be Good, Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Juſt, was never known to have uſurp'd upon the Laws, that his compaſſionate Nature had induc'd him to pardon Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98237:20"/> of his Foes, that he diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted Juſtice impartially to all his Subjects; that he was mild, eaſy, humble, ſtudious of the publick good of his People, that the mildneſs of his Reign did not ſuit with the ſtubborn Nature of the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet that therefore he was not to turn Rebel, and by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Wicked, run po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularly diſtracted: That in caſe he were a Tyrant, oppreſſed the Peoples Priviledges, changed their Religion, and brought in the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſite;</hi> yet his part was no more than to mourn and lament, and look upon him as a Scourge from Heaven for their Sins, but that Nature, as well as a Subjects Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duty to a Sovereign, would curb and hinder him from entertaining any ill Deſign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his King and Father. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, continued he, what have his Favour and Indulgence left
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98237:21"/> me more to deſire? he has always prevented and foreſtall'd my very Wiſhes; The Crown, then paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, he perſued, though not without a Sigh, you know juſtly belongs to a more deſerving Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom you know is born in the Right Line, whom you know ſtands poſſeſt of all the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Virtues that can endear a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign to the Eyes and Hearts of all Mankind, eſpecially to the brave and good; the Enemies of our Countrey know his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, the King his Loyalty, and the World his Fame, the offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Crowd his Mercy, and his Friends extol and proclaim his Truth. Thus, continued he, I have no reaſon to complain that Heaven gave me no pretence to a Throne, ſince what people could be more bleſt in ſuch a Prince as <hi>David,</hi> and ſuch a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour as <hi>Solomon?</hi> yet I could
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98237:21"/> have wiſh'd (ſaid he again with a ſigh) that Fate had either rais'd my Birth higher, or debas'd my mind lower, that I had been born in a legal way, and that I had got the ſtart of <hi>Solomon</hi> in the World, for I find my temper too aſpiring for the Circumſtances of my Birth and Station; I find in me <hi>David</hi>'s Blood too ſtrong and prevailing to be allayed by that of my Mother. In ſhort, I find my Soul perpetually whiſpering in me, that deſire of Greatneſs in a Godlike Sin.</p>
               <p>When Hell's Miniſter ſaw him thus ſtaggering, he plyed him with freſh Attacks, and accoſted him in this manner. Do you think the all-wiſe and all-bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God has imparted all thoſe Prodigious Gifts to you in vain? No undoubtedly, they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd for a Throne, they were deſtin'd to fill the World with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98237:22"/> Wonders of your Reign, and every action of your Life, and every Argument you have us'd do confute your Words, ſecond my Wiſhes, and prove my Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Not that <hi>David</hi>'s Gentle Temper is to be deſpiſed, but it is a greater Virtue in a private Perſon, or an Eccleſiaſtick than a Soveraign, and a Maſculine Soul is certainly fitter for a <hi>Throne.</hi> Has not his eaſy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture induc'd him to make ſuch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Grants to his never ſatisfyed Subjects, that now nothing will content them but the Throne it ſelf? Let the Kingdom be now in never ſo much Peril from the formidable and encroaching Power of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> let <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes be never ſo much oppreſs'd and ruin'd for want of aſſiſtance from <hi>David,</hi> yet the Inſatiate <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> will contribute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the publick relief with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98237:22"/> 
                  <hi>David</hi>'s lopping off and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing on them a limb of his Prerogative. Thus I'le take care by plying him with new Plots or plunging him into ſome expenſive War, to bring him into ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity as that he ſhall be forc'd to ſell and give us his beſt and trueſt Friends, whom I have already ſo ordered the buſineſs as to look upon as <hi>Jebuſites</hi> and <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Penſioners. And when we have ſtript him of thoſe, our next work ſhall be to purchaſe the Succeſſor, whom my contrivances have ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized and rendered obnoxious to the State, and have turn'd all his Virtues like a Battery to his own ruine. Thus we will in time bring <hi>David</hi> to that extremity, that he ſhall for want of Moneys be forc'd to agree to the excluſion of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and paſs your Title into Law: Wherefore your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs now will be to urge your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98237:23"/> Filial Right, the Publick Good, a Prevention of Change of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip, an hinderance to the Uſurpation and Oppreſſion of Liberties and Properties; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be bigotted and ſeduced by a Natural Love, hearken to the Univerſal Call, the eyes of all Mankind are upon you, and by this courſe you not only ſtudy the People's Happineſs and fulfil their Wiſhes, but you likewiſe ſecure your ſelf from ruine; for do you imagine that ſo ſevere, ſo wiſe, ſo penetrating a Prince as the next Heir is, does not ſee through all your Artifices, does not mark the Progreſs you make in People's Hearts? undoubtedly he does, and takes notice of the leaſt ſtep you take, and will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion reſent it, with a Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, which ſelf-defence will prompt him to; for he can never think himſelf ſafe and ſecure,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98237:23"/> when he is in poſſeſſion of the Throne, as long as you poſſeſs the hearts of the People; wherefore the ſame ſelf-defence the prime Law of Nature, obliges you to enter into ſuch meaſures, as may ſecure your own and your friends Lives, and prevent the dreadful Conſequences of a <hi>Jebuſites</hi> Sway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scepter. Wherefore put in practice all the Arts that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the keeping people up to the ferment they are in, let no occaſion ſlip for the promoting a Rebellion, try your Title while your Father is ſtill living, and give out, that you take up Arms only in the King's Defence; and thus having ſecur'd his Perſon, doubt not of ſucceſs, for thereby you ſecure your Cauſe.</p>
               <p>This Advice was moſt pleaſing to <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s mild Diſpoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion; and Ambition had that Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant over him, that he could no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98237:24"/> longer reſiſt the Allurements of a Throne, nor hold from joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Achitophel</hi> in his wicked Deſigns and Councils. This hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Miniſter acquainted him with the Character and Part each Inſtrument had in the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Conſpiracy: Told him, that as he knew <hi>Zimri</hi> was one of the greateſt Wits of the Age; ſo being a Man diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Court, for that one of his own Creatures, when he was Principal Miniſter, was now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before him, and inveſted with all thoſe Honours and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Truſt, that he thought himſelf ſecure in the Enjoyment of. <hi>Zimri,</hi> continued he, with his Wit and Drolling, now is capable of jeſting ſome People into an ill Opinion of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts, and wheedling others into favourable Sentiments of us and our Cauſe. And then for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98237:24"/> 
                  <hi>Nadab,</hi> ſaid he, never could there have been found a fitter man for our Ends: He is ambitious, high Spirited, reſtleſs, and in Want; well vers'd in our Laws, has an indifferent good Pen, and has a peculiar Gift of Canting, which you know takes much with the meaner ſort of <hi>Jews;</hi> ſo that this Man will do us great Service, both in preaching up, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting People into Sedition; thus by ſupplying his Wants, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering his Ambition with conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Preferments, he will prove a Drudge to the Cauſe, and a great Promoter of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts. <hi>Jonas</hi> fam'd through the whole Land for his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Statutes, being diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Court, for that he is not advanced to ſuch Places of Truſt which he fancies his Merit allows him to lay claim to; will be very ſerviceable to us in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98237:25"/> our Undertakings, for that he has a particular Talent of wreſting the Statutes to mean Rebellion, and of making Treaſon juſt and conſiſtent with the Laws of the Land. But a main Engine for the carring on our Plot, will be <hi>Shimei:</hi> A man, tho' not prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of his Money, yet of his Gall and Curſes againſt Monarchy and Kings; and who will be as laviſh of his Time and Pains, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the Government, as he is niggardly and ſparing of his Pelf to relieve the Poor, ſuccour the Needy, or help the Orphan and Widow. This Man, I'll take care ſhall be choſen a Magiſtrate of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and he'll be ſure, in caſe any of opur Friends ſhould fall within the Clutches of the Law, to pack ſuch a Jury of Diſſenting <hi>Jews,</hi> as ſhall make no Conſcience of violating their Oaths, to free our Partiſans from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98237:25"/> the Puniſhments that are inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Criminals of State. But our Maſter-piece is <hi>Korah,</hi> who tho' a Weaver's Son, yet I doubt not but that his performances in this Buſineſs, will make his name live to all Ages. He has been long preparing for the part he is to act. I once made him pretend himſelf a <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> that ſo getting Acquaintance with thoſe of that Sect, he might be the more able to varniſh with probabilityu the Matters he is to atteſt. This. Fellow's Livelihood muſt depend on his Evidence; and he ſhall not only ſwear, that the Queen and the next Heir are in the Plot againſt the King; but that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> himſelf does conſpire with them, and the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> againſt himſelf: How improbable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this may ſeem to thinking perſons, yet the <hi>Jews</hi> are of a temper ſo greedily to ſwallow
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98237:26"/> all that provokes and tends to the raiſing Sedition and Tumult. The next he repreſented to the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous youth, was <hi>Iſhban,</hi> whoſe trade had long been to cheat the People; but now undertakes to reform the State. This man was rivall'd in his Wickedneſs by <hi>Belial,</hi> who tho' he had been ſeveral times par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by his Prince, yet during the time of his Government of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he was perpetually brewing Treaſon and Rebellion againſt his Sovereign and the State. <hi>Rabſheka</hi> too made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable figure in the Roll, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly a Saint affecting to haunt the Conventicles, but privately the Stews and Bawdy-houſes. A Man given to all manner of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, which he inherited as well as his Seditious Principles from his Father, and to promote a Change he cared not if he ſquandered away the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98237:26"/> of the Orphans, and the Treaſure of the City, whereof he was the Keeper, and ſo he could but contribute to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down Monarchy, he was Death to the Cryes of Diſtreſſed Widdows, and to the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Wives and Children, whoſe Husbands and Fathers groaned under a heavy Captivity amongſt the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and for whoſe Redemption the publick had truſted him with Moneys, which he laviſh'd away contrary to the deſign of the Charitable Donours, for the carrying on the Cauſe. Many more there were of the ſame Kidney and Maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Temper that were Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Promoters of this grand Deſign, whoſe Names and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters it is too tedious to rehearſe, and this taſt of the aforementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is ſufficient to give a gueſsat the Nature and Diſpoſitions of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98237:27"/> the whole Crew. But now it is time that I afford the Reader a ſight of <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel</hi> at one of their Cabals, and give him a proſpect of their Conſults and Debates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42-76" type="pages">
               <p>The place of their Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz, was commonly in ſome publick houſe in the City of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> for this Reaſon, that the flocking thither of ſeveral great Men of their Party, might give Renown to the Cauſe, and eſpecially ſo contrived by <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> that <hi>Abſolom</hi> might be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly ſeen, for that his Looks, Words, and Behaviour, carryed with them that Charm, as inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to inſinuate themſelves into the Hearts of the People, who no ſooner ſaw him than they were inſpired with affection and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The Company being now met, <hi>Achitophel</hi> finding <hi>Abjalom</hi> ſtill wavering, making a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98237:27"/> of taking up Arms againſt his King and Soveraign, fearing too it might be the Deſtruction of the whole Realm, and the Death of the King himſelf, and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver jealous, leſt the pretence of publick good,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they made uſe of, ſhould be practiſed againſt himſelf, and with more reaſon too, ſince he had no lawful Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; to which that Wily Miniſter replyed, with a kind of ſcornful Air; that he thought he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd and deſtroy'd all thoſe vain bogglings of Conſcience, and jealouſies of Conſequences; that he was already advanced too far to retreat now with ſafery, that what would be his ſecurity if he perſued his Career, would be his downfal if he made a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, which was his Popularity and the Aſcendant he had over the Peoples Affections. That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ought to be his only Idol,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98237:28"/> that if he did not conſult his own ſafety, he ought at leaſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how many friends there preſent, and others that were abſent had already engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo far, that they expoſed their Fortunes, their Relations, their Lives, their All for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement; and ſhould he now abandon them and give himſelf and them up a Sacrifice to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment and revenge of an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injur'd enemy, would not only be madneſs to himſelf, but ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to his generous Partizans. This reflexion of his Friends ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and ruine in caſe he <hi>deſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> joyning with his ambition and the love of Glory, which he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied ſhin'd no where ſo bright as on a Throne, determined him to comply with their Inſtances and Importunities, and made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve vigorouſly to proſecute the meaſure they had taken. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98237:28"/> they began to concert mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the well managing and proſecuting their Deſign. It was reſolved in that Meeting, that <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſhould take a Progreſs through the Land, well knowing that the Charms and Popularity of that Prince would invite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to their Party, be a means of ſounding peoples Affections, and of diſtinguiſhing their Friends from their Enemies. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſet forth with all the Splendor and Magnificence ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, was ſaluted in all places with the Shouts and Acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the People; what by his winning Perſonage and Carriage, what by the ſpecious Pretexts of Love and Duty to his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, and due regard to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and redreſs of Grievances, with his many Glorious perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances in the Wars abroad, the whole Land rung with his Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98237:29"/> and the people thought they could never ſufficiently admire and extol a Prince adorned with ſo many perfections. In all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where he paſt, the <hi>Jews</hi> flockt in great Numbers to him, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Joy and Satisfaction they took in the ſight of ſuch a Prince; and he in return, cajol'd them with all the fofteſt Words that Tongue can utter, telling them, that he had been a baniſhed man for their dear ſakes; that his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to prevent their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion by Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had been the Occaſion of his having been cut off from the Succeſſion to the Crown, and had made him incur his Father's Diſpleaſure and Reſentment; that now all their Liberties were to be trodden under Foot by a <hi>Deſpotick Power;</hi> that their Trade was intercepted and invaded by the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Syrians,</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98237:29"/> the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> were bringing in their Idolatry and Abominations. That for his part, he did not in the leaſt regret his Loſs, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſoever it was, ſince his Sufferings only proceeded from his having ſtood up in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Behalf: But that he could not but mourn the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they were in, ſince his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, continued he, with a Sigh, being now in the Declenſion of his Age, and doating on the Charms of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Princeſs, was grown careleſs of his Glory, ſuffered all his Councils to be influenc'd by his Succeſſor, who exalted <hi>David</hi>'s Enemies, and diſoouraged and outed all his Friends. Theſe are Grievances, pruſued he, of ſuch a Nature as cannot be too much lamented, and as he feared, were counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and ſupported by Bribes and Sums of Foreign Coin: That
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98237:30"/> he had hazarded his All, and had already loſt his Offices and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor for their Redreſs: But that he did not repine at <hi>David</hi>'s having given his Right away; but that he could not without Tears reflect at his having ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd away theirs and his own, to the Diſhonour of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Name, to his own Downfall, and their Slavery.</p>
               <p>Such were his uſual Words and Careſſes to the People, who were thus wheedled into a belief, that they could not afford him too much of their pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. Theſe Blandiſhments prepared the way for <hi>Achitophel</hi> to work what he had been long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving. This cunning indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Miniſter was not idle at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> during theſe Occurrences in the Countrey. As he had alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum'd and fill'd the whole Land with Terrour and Conſternation,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98237:30"/> by having ſuborn'd <hi>Corah</hi> to ſwear the Queen and <hi>Solomon</hi> into the Plot with the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> were ſaid to have upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo now finding by the Pulſe of the Nation which way they were inclin'd, he contriv'd, ſet on foot, and promoted an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation, being the ſame thing under an other Name, as the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which had formerly been made uſe of for the excluding and keeping <hi>David</hi> out. Then he fell to ſtir up the People to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for a Meeting of the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim,</hi> and yet underhand took care that ſuch Members ſhould be generally choſen as were Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the Eſtabliſht Religion of the <hi>Jews</hi> and Diſſaffected to the Government. Theſe he knew would never give <hi>David</hi> the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys neceſſary for the Support and Defence of the State, but would
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98237:31"/> embroil matters ſo, as would render the unhinging of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment an undertaking the more eaſy to effect. Beſides, he had other Proſpects in ſetting on foot the Aſſociation and theſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, how directly contrary ſoever they were to Law. For by theſe means he numbred and liſted his Party, and moreover, made them ſeem more ſtrong and numerous to the World than they really were. And having thus ingaged the Male-Contents and Diſſenters in a Conſpiracy, he knew they could not go back, but muſt vigorouſly puſh it on, unleſs they had a mind to fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſevere Penalties and Infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Law. He likewiſe gave out that there was a certain Inſtrument preſerved in a Black Box, being the Contract of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>'s Mother, and a ſettlement of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98237:31"/> the Crown upon the Iſſue he might have by that Lady. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the improbability of this Rumour, and <hi>David</hi>'s proteſting publickly the groundleſſneſs and falſeneſs of it, yet it was very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Deſigns, ſince the people believing what they ardently wiſht for, would by no means be perſwaded of the contrary, and this ſeconding their former Meaſures and Paces, they thought now all their irregular proceedings ſupported and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc'd by Law. Now they began to redouble their Clamors for the convening of the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim,</hi> who were no ſooner met than they fell to voting that all thoſe who were Loyal and Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the ſupport of <hi>David</hi> and the Crown, were Traytors and Enemies to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that all thoſe who contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the relief of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98237:32"/> of the State, were the ſame. In ſhort, all things, Actions, and Perſons, that ſtood up in and tended to the maintenance and preſervation of the Monarchy, were thus tumultuouſly voted and declared Illegal, Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Arbitrary. Thus were all the King's Faithful Miniſters to be baniſh'd from His Perſon, His Succeſſour was voted a <hi>Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,</hi> yet without any proof made of his being ſo, or without any deſire of his declaring himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that point; but they did not ſtop there, they drew up a Bill of Excluſion of the next Heir from the Crown, which they impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd the King to ſign and paſs; declaring it the only means of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the State. But meeting with a juſt oppoſition in this ſo horribly unjuſt requeſt, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, notwithſtanding the King offered to comply with any other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98237:32"/> Expedient, they again declared, I ſay, that there was no other way to prevent any change of the Eſtabliſht Religion, the Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and an Inundation of Arbitrary Government and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. The King in the mean while repeated again and again his Inſtances for the bringing to tryal ſuch of the Lords as were accuſed to have a hand in the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites</hi> Plot, but all to no purpoſe, the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> was Death to wholeſome Counſels, and ruſht on upon matters out of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. The Wiſe and Prudent <hi>David</hi> foreſeeing the miſchievous Conſequences and <hi>confuſion</hi> theſe Exceſſes and Irregularities of that great Body muſt neceſſarily be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with, thought fitting for prevention of thoſe Calamities and ſad Revolutions which in all probability would follow in caſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98237:33"/> they were ſuffered to go on at that rate, to diſſolve them, and iſſue out Orders for the <hi>chooſing</hi> a new <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi> But all to no purpoſe, he found in them the ſame heats and ferments, ſo as that they now ſeem'd to be become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, tumultuary, Debauchees; thus was he conſtrain'd again to ſend them home, and order a new Election, convening them to meet at <hi>Baharim,</hi> in hopes that the change of air might have ſome effect upon their temper, and that being no longer pamper'd and poyſon'd by the ſeditious rout of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> their Debates and Reſolves might proceed with more deliberation and tend more to the publick good. But ſtill he found himſelf diſappointed in his Expectations and pious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He found true, what their Speaker declared at the opening of the Aſſembly, that they were
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98237:33"/> not given to change, which is to be meant of their Seditious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and Principles. Nay, they came thither ſo attended, each Member with ſuch a Guard as ſurpaſſed the King's own, and burſt into ſuch raſh and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Reſolves, that <hi>David</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intimation too under-hand of a Conſpiracy to ſeize upon his Perſon, and that many of the Members came thither ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and ſo ſtrongly attended for that purpoſe, he was again forc'd for his own and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's ſecurity to Diſſolve the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and return in all haſt to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by which means the Seditionaries were fruſtrated in their <hi>Deſigns upon His Perſon.</hi> But nevertheleſs, this did not make them diſcontinue their treaſonable Practices, and they ſcattered abroad Clamours more than ever, ſomenting Jealouſies
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98237:34"/> amongſt the Subjects, declaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the King's Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as if the next Heir and the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> had the whole Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant over his Counſels, they had their <hi>Incendiaries</hi> in all parts of the Kingdom, both for the Preaching up Sedition and ſcattering about Libels for to alienate the hearts of the King's Subjects, and to bring all into Anarchy and Confuſion. Some of theſe Inſtruments were catcht and hang'd up for their pains, which was the leaſt they deſerved, having Libels found about them of ſo horrible a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as was capable of poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and infecting the ſoundeſt part of the People.</p>
               <p>Hereupon <hi>David</hi> thought it fitting and ſeaſonable for the preventing the Malice of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies from producing it's effect to iſſue out a Gracious Declaration, wherein he condeſcended to give
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98237:34"/> his Subjects an account of his Conduct, and the Reaſons he had to Diſſolve the late <hi>Sanhedrims,</hi> juſtly checking them therein for their Irregular Proceedings, and aſſuring his Subjects of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reſolution to maintain the Eſtabliſht Religion, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſetled by Law, and that the Law ſhould be the conſtant Rule he would govern by. This produc'd the good effect he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd; the People remembred the Calamities they groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the time of the late Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Uſurpation, they eaſily perceived the ſame humours were fomenting and nouriſhing the ſame Deſigns, they ſaw the ſame Methods and Meaſures taken and perſued, and ſeveral of the truly Loyal <hi>Jews</hi> had newly had a taſt by the exorbitant Reſolves of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> what a bitter Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment they were to expect, in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98237:35"/> caſe they were allowed to purſue blindly their Career, to their own and the Nations Ruine and Deſtruction. Theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (I ſay) made the Truly Loyal <hi>Iſraelites</hi> bleſs God for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſtowed upon them ſo Wiſe and Prudent a Soveraign, and who was ſo watchful for their good and happineſs here, and their future felicity, by taking care no <hi>Innovation</hi> ſhould be made in the Divine Worſhip, nor no Uſurpation upon their Properties and Eſtates.</p>
               <p>Thus the Loyal flock from all parts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with Praiſe and Thanks to the King for his Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Labour and Vigilance for their ſafety and Repoſe; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that notwithſtanding all the Noiſe, and Clamours, and endeavours of the Enemies of the Publick Peace, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Loyal to him to the laſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98237:35"/> Gaſp, and Sacrifice their Lives and Fortunes in defence of his Perſon and Dignity, and the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in the Right Line,</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding that the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts by theſe means ſhow'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be much ſtronger and far more numerous and conſiderable for Eſtates, and the Figure they made in the Nation, than the Male-Contents and Seditionaries, yet theſe laſt did not deſiſt from their Deviliſh Practices.</p>
               <p>In the mean while <hi>Achitophel</hi> what by his incenſing Speeches in the <hi>Sanhednim,</hi> what by his other Contrivances for the working the People up to a Tumult, as by burning the Golden Calf, and the like, having laid his Deſigns but too open to the eyes of all Mankind, and being likewiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of Treaſon, he was taken into Cuſtody, and committed to cloſe Impriſonment. Amongſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98237:36"/> other things, a Daughter of the Aſſociation was found amongſt his Papers, which though a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of High Treaſon, and that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral points of the like nature were atteſted and ſworn againſt him by ſeveral Credible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, yet the Diſſenting <hi>Jews</hi> having then in their power the impanelling of Juries, they packt up ſuch a number, as whoſe Conſciences would ſuffer 'em to ſee their Soveraign's Life, and the whole frame of the Government in danger of being deſtroyed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than put their Seducer <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> to the hazard of being brought to a fair Tryal, ſhown in his own Colours, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded according to his Deſerts. But are they to blame for this? Were not they themſelves as well engaged as he in the Conſpiracy? And no Law obliges a Man to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf, they knew their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98237:36"/> own Preſervation conſiſted in his Acquitment, and it was unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to expect they ſhould paſs Sentence upon themſelves, which they fancyed they ſhould have done, had they allowed of the Juſtice of his Impeachment. And people of their Mould and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples always make Conſcience, give way, and ſubmit to Self-Prefervation and Intereſt. And beſides, they thought perhaps, no Man more capable of putting his Houſe in order than himſelf. Thus was the Arch-Traytor again ſet at Liberty, and Canting <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab</hi> too notwithſtanding all the Proofs that were brought againſt them. Several other Diſſenters too were releaſed, maugre the notoriouſneſs of their Crimes, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Law the Seditionaries had taken care to have paſs'd ſome time before the breaking out of the Plot, by this Law in caſe of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98237:37"/> Bail offered, no Man could be detained in Priſon, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction would never ſuffer their Partizans to want that upon any Occaſion. Thus Law and Juſtice were perverted in theſe wicked Men's hands, the Cauſe was their Golden Calf, and they thought it no Crime to Sacrifice their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, their Repute, nay, the Honour of the Nation (ſince it bred almoſt a Deteſtation of the <hi>Jews</hi> in Forreigners, in that it was capable of Producing and Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a pack of Monſters; ſo that they could but compaſs their Ends, and bring about their long deſired and tugg'd for Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. They ſtill had in mind the ſweetneſs they had taſted in the Sequeſtration of the Loyal <hi>Jews</hi> Eſtates, they long'd to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at pillaging and plundering, and they cared not what Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſoever they might bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98237:37"/> the Realm, ſo they but attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Inſatiate Luſt of Power and Arbitrary Executions, this was the ſcope of all their Wiſhes, this they drove at in all their Conſults and Cabals, and this they had effected, had not the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Moſt Vigilant Prince that ever God plac'd at any Helm by an unparalelled Conduct diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed their Execrable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
               <p>Theſe Proceedings ſtill more alarumn'd and awaken'd the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Loyal <hi>Jews,</hi> and they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly found no means ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the ſafety of their Prince, their Religion, and their Countrey, then to enter into an Anti-Aſſociation againſt the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineers and Seditionaries. All the Towns, all the Provinces of the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> rung with <hi>Acclamations</hi> of <hi>David</hi>'s Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conduct, offered up their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98237:38"/> Praiſes to God for beſtowing on them ſo good, and ſo Gracious a Prince, and poured forth their Thanks and Acknowledgments to him, for his Pious and Indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Care and Vigilance for their Safety and Preſervation here from all Uſurpations of their Fellow Subjects, and for their Eternal Happineſs hereafter, by hindring their being perverted and ſeduced by any Innovations in their Religious Rights aad Worſhip. Thus <hi>David</hi> began again to recover and eſtabliſh himſelf in the Affections of his Subjects, all that Malignity wherewith the Faction had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to poyſon People's Minds, began to purge away of it's ſelf, their Eyes began to open and ſee clear, and they perceived the Bait, the Lure that was laid to draw them into the ſame ſnares, the ſame Deſolation they had
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98237:38"/> formerly ſo miſerably ſuffered by the ſame means. Then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be aſhamed of, and deteſt the Torrent which they had ſo blindly gone along with before, and their Breaſts were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to contain the Abhorrence they had of theſe Trayterous Courſes, but they expreſs'd it to one another, they humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it to their Prince, offering their Fortunes and Lives a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for his ſafety upon all ocafi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to put a ſtop to the reſtleſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of the Faction to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Peace and Tranquility of the Nation, and to involve it in Anarchy and Confuſion. Theſe Offerings were received by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> with his <hi>accuſtomed</hi> goodneſs; and now ſeeing the ſound part and generality of the Nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiv'd of the injurious Surmiſes they had entertain'd, he thought it now ſeaſonable to recal back
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98237:39"/> the Suffering Heir from <hi>Hebron,</hi> where his Conduct had been ſuch as to quell and deſtroy that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Sedition and Diſcord ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to that People, and found the means to bring plenty into the Land and reduce it to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Calm and Tranquillity than it had for many Ages enjoyed. But the <hi>Hebronites</hi> were not they who alone enjoyed the good Effects of his prudent management of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in that Countrey, the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves were by it ſecur'd from a Torrent and Inundation of Miſery and Confuſion: That upon all Tempeſtuous Junctures, uſed to break in from <hi>Hebron,</hi> upon the Land of <hi>Judah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe freſh and repeated In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s wiſe and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Application for the Good and Welfare of the <hi>Jews,</hi> made them thirſt again for a Sight of the Heir of the Crown: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98237:39"/> they renewed their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Acknowledgment to <hi>David,</hi> upon his Reſolution of calling him back from <hi>Hebron,</hi> and grew jealous, and envied the <hi>Hebro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> the Happineſs of having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed his Preſence, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign Influence of his Wiſdom for ſo long a time.</p>
               <p>Then began the Conſcious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to fall into Deſpair: They perceived all their Wiles, all their Artifices for the working up People to a Civil War, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved abortive, through <hi>David</hi>'s wiſe Government, and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s prudent Councils. They found the Friends of <hi>David</hi> to be ſo many, ſo great, and ſo illuſtrious, that all their Arts and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, could not in the leaſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, or come in compariſon with their Zeal and Vertues. <hi>Barcellai</hi> had long flouriſhed in the Roll of Fame for his conſtant
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98237:40"/> Loyalty to the Crown, had once ſacrific'd his vaſt Fortune and his Eaſe in its Defence; and was no leſs celebrated for his Vertues and his Learning, than for his Performances in War, and his Conqueſts over <hi>David</hi>'s Enemies. Glorious too he was in a Son, who had fill'd the World with wonder at his Conduct and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in Naval Combates, and by Land had put a Stop to <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s dreadful Power, and impetuous Progreſſes lower <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates. <hi>Zadock</hi> the High Prieſt, had been conſtantly watchful ſince his promotion to that high Office, to preferve the Ark from Schiſms and Innovations. <hi>David</hi> knowing his Zeal and Worth, had advanc'd him to that high Dignity, notwithſtanding he had carefully ſhunn'd all Power and Grandeur. The <hi>Zogan</hi> too of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who deſcended of a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98237:40"/> noble Race, did as nobly aſſert the Rights of the Church and State againſt all Factious and turbulent Invaders; and the Prophets Sons being led on by ſuch Examples, were bred up in Loyalty, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Religion and Vertue. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai</hi> a conſtant Friend of <hi>David</hi> in all Storms and Tempeſts of State: his Native Excellencies were poliſhed in his very Youth, by Foreign Treaties and Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations; and <hi>David</hi> found by his Management of thoſe Matters he then entruſted him withal, his great Capacity for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and officiating thoſe high Offices he beſtowed upon him at home. Neither was he deceived in his Expectations: For his fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Care ſupplied the Neceſſities of the State, when the Treaſury was at the loweſt Ebb. <hi>Jotham,</hi> a Man of vaſt Copiouſneſs, and penetration of Wit, gifted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98237:41"/> Compariſon by Nature, and form'd by Arts and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to perſwade and prevail over the Hearts and Affections of Aſſemblies. <hi>Bezaliel,</hi> whoſe Command was over the <hi>Kenites</hi> Rocky Province: Him Nature had ſo abundantly ſtock'd with all Advantages in its Diſpoſal, that Education and Learning found him compleat and in no need of their Conjunction to render him perfect. He had all the Vertues, without any of the Vanities which uſually attend them, and had the Happineſs too to ſee all his Glories copied in his Son. <hi>Abdael</hi> adorn'd with all his Father's perfections, who had reſtor'd <hi>David</hi> to the Crown without ſo much as the loſs of one ſole <hi>Iſraelite. Abdael</hi> the Head and Governour over the Prophets School, purſued his Father's Foot-ſteps, and by his undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98237:41"/> perſeverance in his Fidelity to his Prince, made the Faction conſcious how impoſſible it was to bring about their Ends as long as the Crown was ſurrounded, and ſupported by Friends of ſuch a temper. <hi>Eliab,</hi> who had long wander'd and partak'd with his Royal Maſter in all his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings abroad, and had been firm to him in all thoſe ſad and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Perſecutions of Fortune: For which, and ſeveral other Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he was rewarded with the Charge of the Royal Houſhold, and had his only Heireſs deck'd with all the Pride and Beauties of Nature, united to young <hi>Othri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, David's</hi> Son, and the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reſtorer of his Father's youth, and likewiſe was celebrated by the Principal among Foreign Authors for one of the greateſt Miniſters of his Age. <hi>Helon,</hi> tho tempted by <hi>Pharoah,</hi> with all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98237:42"/> Glories, Allurements and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of his Court; and tho an <hi>Egyptian</hi> too by Birth, yet he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned his Countrey, refus'd the tempting Offers of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and ſlighted his Idols to give himſelf to <hi>David,</hi> bringing with him ſuch a Vertue, that neither Profit or Example could ſeduce or betray. <hi>Sheva,</hi> than whom none was more Loyal and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to defend the Prerogatives of the Crown, to render Sedition and Turbulency odious and in their true Colours, to undeceive the People of thoſe Shams and Frauds that were palm'd upon them by the Factious <hi>Scribes,</hi> and to purge away thoſe venemous and ſeditious Humors and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers which the Faction were always infecting the Tribes with. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> who in Charming Numbers ſung the People into Loyalty; and by as keen Satyrs
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98237:42"/> made thoſe who obſtinately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in their Evil Practices, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of their Doings, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to the and Deteſtation of others, Theſe were the principal of thoſe who ſtood in the Breach, and dar'd the Fury of the Seditionaries, when their hopes of Succeſs were at the higheſt, and they thought themſelves in a fair way to bring about their miſchievous and wicked Contrivances. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was ſenſible how difficult a Task it would be to make way to the Crown through ſo brave a Band: And therefore to remove this Guard, they voted many of them in the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> Enemies to the King and Kingdom, and addreſs'd to <hi>David</hi> to have them diſcarded from their Attendance upon his Perſon, and baniſhed from their places in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; but <hi>David</hi> was too well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98237:43"/> with their Worth and their Zeal, for his and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys Welfare and Service, to give them up a Sacrifice to the inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate Rage of a mutinous and rebellious Multitude. He knew that as long as his Throne ſtood upon ſuch a Foundation as their Loyalty and Affections, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies not only to Monarchy, but to all Government and Order, would never, notwithſtanding all their Malice, be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, the Seditious maugre the little Proſpect they had of Succeſs, left not off in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triguing and caballing againſt the State, trying by all poſſible Means to embroil Affairs, ſeduce Peoples Affections, and raiſe in them a Jealouſie and Umbrage of the Government. For that purpoſe <hi>Ben-Jochanan</hi> the Levite was ſet to work. This Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98237:43"/> of mean Birth, and brought into Want by a Marriage, or a Wife out of the Dregs of the people, tho indeed ſuitable to his own Extraction, turn'd <hi>Renega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> and became a violent Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary and Promoter of Sedition. The Faction taking hold of his Want, and the Sordidneſs of his Temper, pickt him out for an Inſtrument; and his Buſineſs was to frame a parallel between the Illuſtrious Heir, and that Grand Apoſtate, who firſt ſeduc'd the people to fall down and worſhip the Golden Calf. This piece ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been long and painfully work'd up by him, did, before it was ſent abroad, paſs the Teſt and Scrutiny of the principal Hands of the Faction. His main Scope and Deſign was to breed a Jealouſie in the people of the Governments being inclined to favour a Change of Religious
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98237:44"/> Rites and Worſhip, and to bring in the Ancient Superſtitions and Idolatries of the <hi>Jebuſites:</hi> And then it proceeded to aſſert, that in caſe of ſuch a Change and Innovation, it was lawful for the people to oppoſe and divert by main Force of Arms, all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Efforts that tended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and if by any Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances it could be ſurmized, that the Government perſevered in ſuch a Deſign or Reſolution, that then it was lawful for the People to depoſe and kill ſuch a Prince, and alter the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be it what it will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76-120" type="pages">
               <p>This piece nicking the Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, was mightily cryed up by the Party, though all Men of Sence and Reaſon, deteſted it's Doctrine and Abhorr'd the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel and Draught. Beſides, the thing it ſelf was but ſhallow and no Bugbear, and not over fit for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98237:44"/> the purpoſe they deſign'd it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the care that had been taken to make it a Prodigy of a Book. For it was rather a Panegyrick upon the Apoſtate, and a defence of Apoſtacy, then a Satyr againſt thoſe who aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the true Religion. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps this is the only inſtance that the Author or the Faction ever gave of Modeſty. And indeed, with what face could they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt Apoſtacy, when they themſelves were guilty of it in the higheſt Degree, for they were not only Apoſtles to their Soveraign, to their Nation and their Government, but alſo to their Religion and their God. And therefore it is no wonder if they endeavoured to maintain and ſcatter abroad ſuch deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and abominable Tenets as were not only deſtructive to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, but to all Government
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98237:45"/> and order in the World. But Peoples Eyes being too well ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and their Affections to the Government too ſtrong, to be enſnared by ſuch courſe Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems and ſuch thin nets, they haunted about for new Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, endeavouring by all the means imaginable to get ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates choſen in all great <hi>Towns</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as were affected to their Party, and hinking by that courſe to fetter up the Courſe of Juſtice, and thereby to prevent a juſt revenge upon all their Crimes. But the Loyal <hi>Jews</hi> were now grown ſo ſenſible of the Deſtructive Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of the Faction, and ſo fearful and apprehenſive of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling again into the ſame Ruine and Calamities, they had but ſo lately groaned under, by the ſame Men, who made uſe of the ſame Pretences and the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98237:45"/> to decoy them into Miſery and Deſtruction. I ſay, being warn'd by their paſt Sufferings and Deſolations, they vigorouſly ſtood up in defence of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, inſomuch, That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Helliſh cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Contrivances of their Cabals, <hi>notwithſtanding,</hi> all the Zeal and Spirit of the Party, who were reduc'd to that Extremity, as to be in <hi>danger</hi> of being brought to condign puniſhments, in caſe they fail'd of having ſuch Officers and Magiſtrates elected as were of their own Leaven, yet they were diſappointed of their hopes and Expectations, the Loyal <hi>Jews</hi> found out and expos'd their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries and Illegal Proceedings, rendred them odious to the ſound part of the Nation, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch Officers to be choſen, as were zealous for the <hi>True Religion</hi> as then Eſtabliſhed, Aſſerters of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98237:46"/> Monarchy and the Government, Impartial Lovers of Juſtice, and wholly devoted to the good and intereſt of their Countrey. This heightned the Factions Deſpair, they were now at a terrible <hi>plunge,</hi> and knew not well what Courſe to take, but the rancour they had ſowed had taken ſuch deep root, that a great part of the Mobile of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had ſtill ſo much of the <hi>Infection</hi> left in them, that they were ready upon all <hi>occaſions</hi> to fall upon ſuch Officers of Juſtice, who came to put the Laws in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution upon ſuch <hi>Criminals</hi> as were of their Party, and had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred Penalties by their Miſ-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour and their <hi>Tranſgreſſions.</hi> By theſe means ſeveral were reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued from <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and the Laws hindred from being put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. But though they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that this could not long ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them, they ſtill continued
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98237:46"/> to uſe all manner of means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to alienate the Peoples Hearts and Affections from the King and his Heirs. There had formerly appeared in the World a Book, Entituled, <hi>The Growth of the Superſtitions of the</hi> Jebuſites, Written by an Ingenious though a diſaffected <hi>Jew.</hi> This ſame piece had met with a favourable Reception amongſt the <hi>Jewiſh Male-Contents,</hi> and a <hi>Continuation</hi> of it was at this time thought pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to revive the Umbrages of the People; amongſt other things it endeavoured to perſuade, that there had long been a Secret League and Treaty between <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> and the Monarch of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> whereby <hi>David</hi> was oblig'd amongſt other Articles to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Worſhip of the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> and that for that purpoſe <hi>Pharoah</hi> ſhould aſſiſt him with Men and Money, and likewiſe, to make
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98237:47"/> himſelf abſolute over the Lives and Eſtates of his Subjects. A mad, ridiculous ſham and <hi>inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For it was a thing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ever to bring in and eſtabliſh the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> without wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the <hi>Jews,</hi> and certainly never any <hi>Prince</hi> out of an Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ſome few particular <hi>Men,</hi> and a <hi>Sect</hi> deſtructive to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and <hi>Dependant</hi> on a Forreign Head would deſtroy the main Body of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and leave himſelf without Subjects and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. And as for the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought in by the <hi>Conſent</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is a thing never to be ſuppos'd, ſince their very Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were the Ancient Poſſeſſions of the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> would certainly never allow of their Return, whom they had deprived of their <hi>Inheritance,</hi> well knowing they would never be content until they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98237:47"/> in them again, and that <hi>Baal</hi> not only claimed their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but their Lands too. And as for <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s contributing his aid and ſuccour to the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> for the reſetling them and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> it is well known he has always been too great a Slave to his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and Grandeur to commit ſuch a Soleciſm in Politicks, as to put Arms into ſuch a hand as of all <hi>Aſia,</hi> was alone capable of putting a ſtop to his Prodigious and dreadful Carreer. He knew the temper of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People, the Conſtitution of their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the Infatuation the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> lay under, to be ſuch that they would give no Supplys to the Crown, though in the greateſt Exigencys and neceſſitys of State, out of a frantick and groundleſs fear, that they might be employed to their own Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. He knew too that the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98237:48"/> ſetled Revenues on the Crown were too ſhort and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuffice either ſupporting the Crown it ſelf, upon occaſion, or defending and relieving the Allies and Confederates of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> againſt the ſpreading and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Arms of <hi>Egypt;</hi> though his Wealth and Revenues were vaſt, he employed them ſuch ways as more contributed to his Grandeur and the Enlargement of his Empire. He brib'd and made Penſioners of a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Jews,</hi> who pretending Zeal and Friendſhip to the State and Government, yet at the ſame time maliciouſly inſinuated into the People, that there were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns on foot at Court to Uſurp their Sacred Rites and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the Royal Family were inclinable to <hi>Baal</hi>'s Superſtitions and Idolatry, that with it Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Arbitrary Power was to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98237:48"/> be introduced. By ſuch like Wiles and Artifices as theſe were the Choſen People ſeduced to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an ill Opinion of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and upright Patriots, and to cry up, and extol thoſe Traytors to their Countrey, who by ſuch Courſes created thoſe Diviſions amongſt the <hi>Hebrews</hi> as weakned them and rendred them uncapable of oppoſing the Growth of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s King. They were the Perſons who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſell and bring upon their Countrey Slavery, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, notwithſtanding their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming againſt the Government, as uſurping upon their Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Charters. They were the occaſion of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates being oppreſs'd and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run. They by brooding ſuch Jealouſies and Diviſions, laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the only door that could let in the <hi>Jebuſite.</hi> All the Gracious
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98237:49"/> Declarations of <hi>David,</hi> all his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances to maintain their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and defend their Religion by Law Eſtabliſhed, were not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory to this Inſatiate Party, for that Religion and Priviledge were only the Ingredients they made uſe of, to work the People into a Ferment, and then by a <hi>continual Application</hi> of Fears and Jealouſies, to ſcrue 'em up into a Rage and Fury, the <hi>Conſequences</hi> whereof they knew would be <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Anarchy:</hi> This they look'd upon as the readieſt way to build their Fortunes, which if they could attain to, they cared not though it were upon their Father's <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> They long'd to be <hi>Lording</hi> and <hi>Domineering</hi> again over their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Subjects: They had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the Sweets they enjoyed in the <hi>Sequeſtrations</hi> of the <hi>Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts Eſtates,</hi> and ſuch as remained
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98237:49"/> faithful to <hi>David</hi> in his late Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. This was ſport they itch'd to be at again; and therefore all Perſons and things that oppoſed their deſtructive Deſigns, and tended to the preſervation and ſafety of the People and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> theſe Traytors traduced as Enemies to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and exclaim'd againſt them as Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Tooles. Yet theſe very Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were the only Perſons who aimed and exerciſed Arbitrary Power.</p>
               <p>In the ſeveral late Seſſions of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> the Seditionaries having got by Surprize and Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Elections ſeveral of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be choſen Members, all their Reſolves ſavoured of and tended to <hi>Tyranny,</hi> they ſent for up into Cuſtody from all the parts of the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſuch Perſons as upon occaſion teſtified their Zeal for the Crown, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98237:50"/> them without any Cauſe given: And then they voted, <hi>That the next Heir being a</hi> Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, <hi>and the hopes of his coming ſuch to the Crown, hath given the greateſt Countenance and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the preſent Deſigns and Conſpiracies againſt the King and Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Thus they voted the next Heir a <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> which was more than any Man living could tell but himſelf; but in caſe he were, the Wiſemen of the <hi>Jews,</hi> were of Opinion, that the moſt <hi>Prudent and</hi> moſt <hi>Pious</hi> courſe, would have been to have employed all imaginable Care and Art for the reducing him to the True Church, whereas this way of proceeding of theirs could but the more enrage and irritate him againſt the Profeſſors and Doctrine of the True Religion. Beſides that Branch of the Vote that affirms, That the next Heirs
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98237:50"/> being a <hi>Jebuſite</hi> was what gave the greateſt <hi>Countenance</hi> to thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns that were then on foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh Religion,</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what <hi>Corah</hi> had laid down in his <hi>Depoſitions,</hi> who ſaid, that the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> had declared their <hi>Apprehenſions,</hi> that he would not allow of their Deſigns, and therefore after the Blow was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they muſt have been forced to have conſtrain'd him to give his conſent to the Aſſaſſination of the <hi>King</hi> his Father, Maſſacre of his true <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Subjects, firing of his Towns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by pardoning of the <hi>Aſſaſſins,</hi> Murtherers and <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> that then he alſo be poyſoned and deſtroyed, after they for ſome time had abuſed his Name and Title to ſtrengthen in their Plot. All which and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Paſſages in <hi>Corah</hi>'s and other of the <hi>Evidences Narratives</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:98237:51"/> of the Plots, do ſhew they had no Reliance on the next Heir; but that on the contrary, his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Tenderneſs towards the King, would render all their Deſigns abortive.</p>
               <p>Yet upon groundleſs Surmiſes they proceeded to bring in a Bill of Excluſion, notwithſtanding that they well knew, that the Crown of <hi>Judah</hi> was an Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Kingdom or Monarchy, which devolved upon the next Heirs of the Blood Royal, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Election, or Conſent of the People, otherwiſe than by acknowledging their Lawful Right, derived from God, by their Blood to them; and as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly their Hereditary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy was ſet up at firſt, ſo it was afterwards upheld and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by the Providence of God; from which we cannot but infer this Concluſion, That whoever
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98237:51"/> ſhall attempt to alter ſuch a right of Succeſſion without a manifeſt Revelation, is a notorious Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per upon the Right of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who is to ſucceed, be the pretence for it what it will; and a Rebel againſt that Providence which gave him that Right. Nor could the former Rebellious U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furpations and Diſorders be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents to juſtifie thoſe who ſhould begin them again: So that no Humane Power can bar and prevent the next Heir his Succeſſion; but by encroaching upon his Right, and by rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that gave it him. So that be the Inconveniencies that ſhall follow upon ſuch a Succeſſion what they will or can be, the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged to ſubmit to them upon pain of Rebellion, both againſt God and his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And then let any Man be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98237:52"/> Judge, if it be not better to fall into the Hands of a <hi>Jebuſitiſh</hi> Prince, than into the Hands of an angry God, who is a conſuming Fire; and who is not bound by any Act of a <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting a ſinful and rebellious People.</p>
               <p>Not but that the Loyal <hi>Jews,</hi> and even thoſe that were ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized with the Name of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites,</hi> did acknowledge that it would be a great Affliction for them to fall into the Hands of a <hi>Jebuſitiſh</hi> Prince; becauſe of the great and implacable Malice which the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> their whole Sect and Tribe have ever born to the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Religion, which was more eaſily defended againſt them than any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion whatſoever, as being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon greater Antiquity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived immediately from God himſelf, and more conformable
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98237:52"/> to the Doctrines of the Prophes. Wherefore <hi>Baal</hi> and the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> had left no Stone unturned to re-eſtabliſh in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> their Suerſtitions, and root out the <hi>Jews</hi> and the true Religion; and ſticking neither at Perjury, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor any other Villany that they thought might conduce to that end. And when God by his Gracious Providence had defeated all their damnable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, they transformed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Shapes of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting <hi>Jews;</hi> and ſo promoted a Rebellion, which ended in the ſeeming Ruine of the Religion and Government, to their migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Content and Satisfaction: But tho <hi>David</hi> at his Return, re-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled the Church, yet they did not give over; but by a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſpreading Pamphlets and Libels, written in the Stile of the Diſſenting <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſo
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98237:53"/> very acceptable to them, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging all that oppoſed the inteſtine Diviſions; and a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſuch other Frauds, they did in twenty Years time ſo ſhake the Foundations of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church again, that <hi>David</hi> with all his Prudence and Piety could hardly preſerve and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her againſt the <hi>Jebuſitiſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on the one hand, and the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> on the other.</p>
               <p>So that if this poor perſecuted Church, ſhould have fallen into the hands of a Prince of their Communion, ſhe was to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected whatever the moſt enraged Malice, armed with his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity could inflict upon her; and ſhe had all the reaſon in the World to expect the Diſſenters would joyn with them to afflict and ruine her. Not out of any Kindneſs to <hi>Baaliſm;</hi> but out of an implacable hatred they both
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98237:53"/> have conceived againſt her: So that the Ark had all the reaſon in the World to dread that day that ſhould put her into ſuch Hands.</p>
               <p>But ſtill with this Limitation, notwithſtanding that by avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Miſchief, ſhe ſhould not plunge her ſelf into a greater; that is, by flying Perſecution from Men, to fall into a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt her God, by whoſe Providence Kings and Princes, of what Religion ſoever they be, rule; and by whom they have in all Ages been ſo ordered, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and governed, as he in his Divine and Holy Wiſdom ſaw moſt expedient for the Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Chaſtiſement of his Church, to the greater Encreaſe of her Glory, and her Happineſs in the World to come.</p>
               <p>So that the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> could not have proceeded on to the diſinheriting the next Heir, by
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98237:54"/> paſſing a Bill of Excluſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, without doing an Act contrary to natural Juſtice, by running headlong to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before Conviction: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it was before they had heard the Party, or examined any Witneſs about him, at leaſt none in his Defence. And all this without any Law or Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, is without doubt very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. Moreover the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> had their Right from God alone, and no Power upon Earth could deprive them of it. So that the Proceedings of the <hi>Sane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim</hi> in this matter, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely contrary, not only to the Law of God, but the Law of the Land too: For if this Bill had paſs'd, it would have chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the very Eſſence of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and have made the Crown elective: For ſo the ſame reaſon that the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> might
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98237:54"/> have diſinherited that Prince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on meer Surmiſes of his difference from them in Religion, other <hi>Sanhedrims</hi> might have diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted another, upon ſome other Pretence which they might ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt; and ſo conſequently by ſuch Excluſions elect whom they pleaſe. Beſides, this Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion was contrary to thoſe Oaths which all ſuch <hi>Jews</hi> as were in Office, and made any Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the State, were bound to take, and had taken, to be faithful and Loyal to their Kings and Succeſſors. Neither was this the right Courſe to prevent thoſe Calamities they ſo much dreaded; on the contrary, it was the ready way to aſcertain them at <hi>David's</hi> Death with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Civil War; and in all likelihood bring it upon them before that time too: For ſo ſoon as ever the Bill ſhould have paſt,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98237:55"/> the next Heir would have had a Right to have made War upon the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> even in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid's</hi> Life time; and what the Event of that would have been, God only knows. However, to have prevented a Surprize, there muſt have been a Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or an Aſſociation kept up ſo long as the next Heir lived; and what the Conſequences of them might have been was no difficult matter to foreſee; the firſt ruining the Liberties of the People, and the ſecond endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering the Prerogatives of the Crown: And both of them in the divided Condition <hi>Judah</hi> was then in, in point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tending to raiſe ſuch Fears and Jealouſies, as would have been almoſt as uneaſie and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe as a <hi>Jebuſitiſh</hi> Succeſſor; and all this brought upon them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by their raſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98237:55"/> Doings: Whereas the other was only future and contingent: So that <hi>Doeg</hi> in his Infamous Libel, called <hi>The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Jebuſitiſh Succeſſor,</hi> has drawn up the Caſe after a falſe and impious manner; but what could otherwiſe be expected from ſuch a Fellow as would ſell his God for a Meals Meat; and who was only the Arch-Traytor <hi>Achitophel's</hi> Copiſt in the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? But allow the Caſe to be ſo as it is ſtated in that Libel, it would not have juſtified the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſuch a Succeſſor as he hath deſcribed by Force and Arms, againſt his Right, and their Oaths to the contrary, tho' they were never ſo certain to ſucceed in the Attempt; but then that wicked Man has moſt falſely repreſented things to the World; and ſo as it is impoſſible they ſhould ever have proved in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98237:56"/> the Event, if the <hi>Jews</hi> did not give occaſion for it, by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſperous Rebellion.</p>
               <p>For firſt it was agreed on by all the World, that there were ten <hi>Jews</hi> for one <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> thro' all the Dominions of the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſo that if ſuch a Succeſſour ſhould attempt to extirpate them, the bare refuſing to aid and aſſiſt him in ſuch an Enterprize would render it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
               <p>Secondly, All their Laws were in Favour of that Religion which was eſtabliſhed, and which could never be repealed but by the <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> and it's morally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to have a <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> the Major part of which Will not be of the true <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, as eſtabliſhed, who will never conſent to ruine themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98237:56"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The Revenue of ſuch a Prince could not bear the Charge of ſo great an Army, as would have been neceſſary to have reduced the People to a Religion ſo generally hated and deteſted as that was.</p>
               <p>To all which indeed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made Anſwer, That he might have had Foreign Aids; and Secondly, that he would have had the means to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured, deterred, and perverted many from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion to his own.</p>
               <p>As to Foreign Aſſiſtances, no Prince will dare to have ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as ſhall totally over-power his own People, becauſe then they will be able to ruine him; and he may be ſure they will do it, ſelf-Intereſt being the Idol of all the World; ſo that this was a ridiculous Suppoſition in a Prince of their own Nation, who
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98237:57"/> had no other Dominions but thoſe.</p>
               <p>As to any Number of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he might have been able to have brought over to his own Religion, they would have been very inconſiderable in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe who would not have been brought over, tho' the Number were ſuppoſed to have been greater than was likely to be: For that ſome Men have got a Way of reproaching all they hate, with the Name of <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> becauſe there was none more hated than that; yet even for that Caſe the Number muſt have been too ſmall, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unwilling to Liſt themſelves in a hated Party, except they might have had great Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by it; which are not to be afforded to many (in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the reſt) in one King's Reign, in ſo ſmall a Kingdom as that of <hi>Judah.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:98237:57"/>
               <p>Thirdly, the very Attempting of this with force and violence, would have driven ſo many Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of the Nation; as would have deſtroyed both the Princes Revenue and Security, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all Appearances of Reaſon, no Man would have done for his own ſake.</p>
               <p>To this might be added, that it was three to one whether ever the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould have had ſuch a Prince: For who but God could tell whether <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould have ſurvived <hi>David?</hi> But if he did, whether his Intereſt, the Grace of God, and Man's Humane Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, would not have work'd upon him to return to that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he was firſt principled in, and for which, <hi>David</hi> and the whole Royal Family had ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſuffered.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:98237:58"/>
               <p>And after all this, ſuppoſing he ſhould have ſucceeded and have been zealous for his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuppoſe that to be <hi>Baal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm;</hi> there was no neceſſity that he muſt have acted all the worſt Principles of <hi>Baaliſm</hi> to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Degree. It is certain it is not uſual ſo to do, though the difficulty be not ſo great as here it would have been.</p>
               <p>And after all, Doth not the Providence of God govern the <hi>Jebuſitiſh</hi> as well as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Is the Arm of the All-migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhortned, that he can neither deliver nor ſupport his Ark? Or had he forſaken her in her Old Age, who preſerved her with ſo much Care and Power in her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy under Heathen Princes? Do we believe the <hi>Prophets?</hi> Do we believe the <hi>Jewiſh Religion</hi> is acceptable to him? Are the far greateſt part of them that profeſs
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98237:58"/> it, ſincere or falſe in their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? If all this be anſwered one way, they have ſomething more to rely upon, than the Faith and Religion of <hi>Princes?</hi> If in the other, it would have been but folly to pretend to ſecure by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Arts, that which God was reſolved to deſtroy.</p>
               <p>But then ſhould we grant that the hopes of the next Heir's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Jebuſite</hi> to the Crown, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally given the greateſt encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Jebuſites Plot,</hi> would the <hi>Diſ-inheriting</hi> him have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated thoſe hopes? No, But it would rather have whetted them on to do their utmoſt to Murther the <hi>King,</hi> to prevent or revenge that injury to the next Heir and their long'd for <hi>Succeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that if any Man would but in cold blood conſider on all the <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> he muſt neceſſarily conclude,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98237:59"/> That if ever <hi>Faction, Anger,</hi> and <hi>Ill-Deſigns</hi> were entertained by ſo great a Body of Men as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> was, it is apparent they were here. Of which it will not be unſeaſonable to inſtance, but in ſome few <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Could ever any Man produce either Precedent or Law to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Impriſonment of thoſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and Loyal <hi>Jews,</hi> who publickly declared their Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Irregular, Tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Trayterous Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Faction?</hi> Had the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſort of people of all the twelve Tribes a Right to Petition the King againſt his Expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, in a thing of which he was the ſole Judge by all the Laws of the Land? and might not ſuch as repreſented the <hi>King's Perſon,</hi> or otherwiſe officiated in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, oppoſe them, or which
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98237:59"/> is leſs, diſown thoſe Irregular Proceedings? But ſuppoſe they did more than they ought in this their Oppoſition, was it fit to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them before they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to defend themſelves, and urge what they had to plead in their Juſtification? But being it ſerved thoſe Gentlemen's turn at that time, they made uſe of it, without conſidering, that it might one day be turn'd againſt them themſelves, and then how ſevere a Task it would be to brook it. The Towns and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations of the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> did ſend generally the principal of their Tribes and Hundreds, but if this Precedent had once been allowed of, and eſtabliſhed, they might have laid them by when they pleaſed; and have ſent Mechanicks, Tradeſmen, Shop-keepers, and how would their high Spirits have brook'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98237:60"/> to have been ſent for into Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and made to kneel, without being ſuffered to ſpeak, and only for doing their Duties to ſuch Men, and to be ſent home again? Certainly none of the Heads of the Tribes could have brook'd ſuch Indignities, but with ſuch inward Reſentments as befit the generoſity and temper of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or otherwiſe they muſt be thought to have been prepared for Slavery: And all that manly Courage that had made thoſe People renowned in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys in the World, was degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into the moſt ſhameful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminacy and Cowardiſe. Only in this caſe Religion and Loyalty made them yield, even to Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Oppreſſion. As long as God-like <hi>David</hi> thought fit to ſuffer it, they ſubmitted, but with ſuch Thoughts as would have taught the Faction more
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98237:60"/> Juſtice and Moderation, if this had not been in the Caſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, their ſtyling all thoſe Generous <hi>Jews</hi> who were <hi>brought</hi> into the Commiſſions of the Peace, in the room of ſome others diſplaced, <hi>Men of Arbitrary Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Countenancers of Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites and Baaliſm;</hi> and if the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction could have invented more odious Names and Words than theſe, they might with as much truth and ingenuity have beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them upon them. Was it a Priviledge of the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> to vote a Man a Philiſtine or an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian,</hi> or that thoſe who they thought fit were the Men, who occaſioned the Breach before <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and his <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the occaſion of all his former Troubles? If it were ſo, there was no more to be ſaid, but only to beg their pardon, and to kneel down at the Bar of the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:98237:61"/> with the ſame ſubmiſſion as if one had believed the Speaker Infallible, and every Member an Angel. But if their Votes were bound to be not only conſonant to Law, but agreeable to the truth of things, then that Paſſage was haſtily and paſſionately writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and not well conſidered; and will be an admoniſhment to them that they take ſuch care for the future as to write more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, and ſpeak and vote like men, that had a little reſpect to their Places.</p>
               <p>Was ever any thing ſo extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant as their Vote concerning <hi>David's</hi> Revenues and his bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing of Money upon them? Might not a Loyal <hi>Jew</hi> have lent the King a Talent or two with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their leave, and not incur the danger of being reputed an Enemy to the meeting and ſitting of <hi>Sanhedrims?</hi> Suppoſe the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98237:61"/> 
                  <hi>Egyptians</hi> or the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> ſhould have made an Invaſion into the Land of <hi>Iſrael</hi> or <hi>Judah,</hi> or the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> or Diſſenting <hi>Jews</hi> have riſen, and <hi>David</hi> have wanted Money to have ſuppreſſed the One, or have driven out the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, muſt the Loyal <hi>Jews</hi> have hazarded His or their own Ruine, rather than ſupply him by a Loan in the Intervalls of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> had not they a Property in what was their own, and might not they uſe it as they ſaw Cauſe, without breach of Priviledge of <hi>Sanhedrims?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They Voted too, That the Proſecution of the Diſſenting <hi>Jews</hi> upon the Penal Laws, <hi>Was at that time grievous to the Subject, a weakning of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Intereſt, an Encouragement to</hi> Baaliſm, <hi>and dangerous to the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> And this Vote is as incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible as any of the reſt.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98237:62"/> Why was it made? To what Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is it grievous? To the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters? why then let them leave their Diſſenting to the Ark and all will be well. What <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Intereſt doth it weaken? Doth it weaken the <hi>Jewiſh Intereſt</hi> that is ſetled by Law? Then why did they not ſay ſo? But how it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged <hi>Baaliſm,</hi> or endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Peace of the Nation, was yet harder to be underſtood? But ſuppoſe it did; What then? They might repeal the Bills they had on Foot, that would have repealed them, if they might but have paſſed; but they were to be Adjourned, and had not time to finiſh them: And did they think to have laid them aſleep by their ſingle Vote, without the Conſent of the Elders, or of the King? They ſhould have done well then to have told the Nation that they had the Legiſlative Power in their
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98237:62"/> own hands, and that it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law for any Man to act againſt a Vote of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> tho' in obedience to the Laws of the Land.</p>
               <p>Now if they had carryed theſe few points in this Seſſion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Not only to deny the King any Supply, but to make it Criminal for any Man to lend him Money upon his Revenues, they might then in another Seſſion have gone further, and have made it puniſhable for any Man to have paid him his juſt, ſetled, legal Dues; and that would have made them able to have forced the King or his Succeſſors to what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever they had pleaſed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They might have proceeded to impriſon <hi>David's</hi> Subjects in an illegal and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary way, for Matters that had no Relation to Priviledges of <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> they might afterwards
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98237:63"/> have extended this to as many perſons and things as they had pleaſed; and ſo no man would have dared to have ſtood by <hi>David</hi> againſt a <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> tho' they had attempted to depoſe him. Nor would <hi>David</hi> in a ſhort time have been able to have protected his Subjects againſt any Injury that they, or any of them had been pleaſed to have done them; which would infallibly have ſubverted the Monarchy, and have introduced a Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If they had got that great Branch of the Legiſlative Power into their Hands, of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending the Execution of Laws by their Votes, they might have driven it as far as they pleaſed, and ſo have outed the King and the Elders as a former <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> did by the ſame means.</p>
               <p>Theſe and a thouſand other
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98237:63"/> Circumſtances concurring to make all unbiaſſed and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding People ſuſpect, nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there was a Plot of the Diſſenting <hi>Jews</hi> upon the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion, as by Law eſtabliſhed: the Loyalliſts began to rowze up, and by their vigorous Zeal and Vigilance to ſupport the Throne and State, defeated the Deſigns of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whoſe Weakneſs and Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs they expoſed, and made appear their own Strength and Numbers, to exceed beyond all Compariſon thoſe of the <hi>Seditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries,</hi> who now having loſt all Hopes of retrieving their Cauſe, began to ſhift for themſelves, leſt a longer Stay might have expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to the juſt Fury and Reſentment of the Law.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all thoſe Sculkers and Fugitives, none had more reaſon to look out be time for a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98237:64"/> ſafe Retreat from a juſt revenge than the wicked <hi>Achitophel:</hi> He had been the helliſh Contriver of all thoſe Deviliſh Machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Peace, Wellfare, and Tranquility of the State: But how heinous ſoever the Sins of the People were, Heaven out of its abundant goodneſs, thought not fit to puniſh them ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to ſuffer them to be the ſecond time plung'd into the dreadful Calamities of a <hi>Civil War,</hi> as they had like to have been by that Impoſtor of a Patriot.</p>
               <p>Thus all Proſpect of Succeſs, in his Deſigns being vaniſhed, the People irritated and enraged againſt him for the Deſolations they had like to have fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by his means, &amp; juſtice gaping after Revenge for ſo many dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Effects of his Diabolical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, he reſolved for <hi>Tyre,</hi> where ſeveral of his Tools were
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98237:64"/> gone before out of the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Self-Security, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for his Reception.</p>
               <p>Yet firſt he was to take his Leave of haughty <hi>Jezabel.</hi> Being come to her for that purpoſe, he let her know, both by his Looks and Words the Torment and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh he lay under, for having been ſo diſappointed in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Endeavors to pull down Monarchy, and ſet up his and her Creatures in its Stead. He told her, he had riſqued not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life, Body and Soul for that purpoſe; but that he had more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over inveigled his Friends into the ſame Perils and Dangers, and had hazarded the utter ruine of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> for her Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts. She let him know how ſenſible ſhe was of his good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, that ſhe was well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he had uſed all the tricks and Stratagems of Policy, for the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98237:65"/> promoting her end, and that ſince he had done all that lay in the Power and Art of Man, they had only to complain of their Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the diſappointment, and that he ſhould find in her all the acknowledgment his good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours deſerved. That ſhe approved of his deſign of taking Refuge at <hi>Tyre,</hi> where ſhe knew he would be moſt welcome to a little Siſter ſhe had there, who had been always his Darling, and ſhe always mindful of his good Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for her Promotion. That <hi>Tyre</hi> was the only place of ſafe retreat for him, ſince her other Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at <hi>Hebron</hi> was become an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate to their Cauſe and Blood, being by the Charms of <hi>David's</hi> Reign deluded into a fondneſs and good Opinion of Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And as for her other little Siſters they were not in a Capacity to ſhelter him from the juſt reſentment of an incenſed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98237:65"/> Prince, that ſhe her ſelf would only ſtay till ſhe had ſetled her Affairs, and then would follow him to his Sanctuary, where he ſhould receive from her ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns as correſponded more with his Endeavours, than the Iſſue of his Deſigns. Thus after many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like kind and tender Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and Aſſurances, he took his leave and departed for <hi>Tyre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But at his Arrival there, he found himſelf again diſappointed in his Expectations, for the little Siſter inſtead of receiving him with thoſe Careſſes and Blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhe uſually welcom'd People with of his Temper and Kidney, gave him but a cold and poor <hi>entertainment.</hi> She ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the <hi>Perſecutions and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities</hi> ſhe had ſuffered by the means of his <hi>Counſels,</hi> ſhe ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred his Speech in the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim,</hi> preſſing her ruine, and which indeed brought her to the Brink
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98237:66"/> of <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> ſo that it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to expect ſhe could <hi>look</hi> favourably upon a Man whom ſhe had ſo many Reaſons to hate and deteſt, and who was ſo far from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true affection to any <hi>one,</hi> or any Society ſoever, that he has always prov'd the very beſt of humane kind, only for the carrying on his own <hi>deſigns</hi> and <hi>Intereſts.</hi> Thus <hi>ſhe</hi> made him ſenſible that <hi>ſhe</hi> ſtill <hi>bore</hi> him a <hi>grudge,</hi> which went ſo to his <hi>heart,</hi> with the diſpleaſure to find all his <hi>Deviliſh Wiles</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> diſplay'd and expos'd to the eyes of all People, to find he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the abomination of all the ſound and honeſt part of <hi>mankind, Achitophel</hi> laying all theſe things to heart, I ſay, put an end to his loathed Life in ſuch wiſe as the World well knows.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:66"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98237:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98237:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98237:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98237:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98237:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98237:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98237:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98237:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98237:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98237:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98237:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98237:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98237:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98237:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98237:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98237:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
